Denis O. Vodopianov

Berlin, Germany \cdot nekto.john.d@gmail.com \cdot https://github.com/grambbledook

About

Software engineer with decade of experience specialising in distributed systems with a focus on scalability, reliability and performance. I have experience both moving from monoliths to microservices to scale a business, and going back to microliths to optimise cost and performance.

I enjoy solving system problems of various kinds as well as low-level algorithmic problems. My key strengths include analytical thinking, empathy, strong bias for action, ownership, and ability to focus on customer needs.

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Kotlin, Java, Scala, Python, Go, Typescript Web Frameworks: Spring Boot, Vert.x, Netty, Play, Express.js

DevOps: Docker, Kubernetes, Terraform, Ansible, Jenkins, Gitlab CI/CD, Argo

CD, Datadog, ELK stack, Grafana, Prometheus

Databases: Postgres, Mongo, DynamoDB, Cassandra, Redis

Networking: TCP/IP, HTTPS, WebSockets

Big Data: Hadoop, Hive, Pig, Hbase, Clickhouse, Storm, Spark, Airflow

Work Experience

Trade Republic Bank

Senior Software Engineer

October 2023 - April 2024 Berlin, Germany

- Was in charge of user accounts and balances. Made system consistent, fast, and highly available.
- Resolved integration issues, and delivered a system required for Cards product launch.
- Identified and fixed slow spots, reduced response latency from 20 to 5 ms.
- Built a reconciliation system that processes 150M transactions daily to keep banking data consistent.

Picsart

January 2022 - March 2023

Senior Software Engineer II (Lead Engineer) - Data Platform

Berlin, Germany

- Owned user tracking component in analytics platform handling billions of events per day, peak 200k eps.
- Implemented edge component with auth and back-pressure mechanisms for analytics platform using Envoy-based API gateway.
- Optimised event ingestion, reduced fleet by 40% and freed up resources.
- Reduced change failure rates by adding quality checks, tests, feature-flags and alerts.
- 10x faster deployments by switching to trunk-based development, reusable CI/CD components.
- Mentored engineers, improved ownership, quality, reduced debt.

N26 GmbH

March 2020 - January 2022

Berlin, Germany

Senior Software Engineer - Identity, Acting Tech Lead

- Full ownership of identity platform with focus on security, scalability, reliability and compliance.
- Implemented strong customer authentication for PSD2 compliance.
- Worked with product and ML on R&D projects, creating a roadmap to improve security of the platform.
- Automated access recovery for non-German customers, improving UX and cutting costs.
- Designed and implemented various authentication mechanisms for n26 products.
- Participated in on-call and incident response, addressing issues and minimizing downtime.

Freelance, Contractor

November 2018 - February 2020

Saint-Petersburg, Russia

Lead Software Engineer at Plutus.ai

- Led a team of five engineers to deliver casual crypto portfolio with gamification and social elements.
- Identified and resolved scalability issues to meet the demands of a growing client base.
- Switched system from batched to NRT data processing, enhanced gamification mechanics.
- Built framework for fast integration with exchanges and news outlets.

EDUCATION

ITMO University

 $Saint-Petersburg, \ Russia$

September 2004 - February 2010

Degree: Master's degree in Optical Electronic Devices and Systems with specialisation in Optical-

Electronic Devices and Systems for Video Information Processing

Qualification: Engineer

Projects

Indoor cycling HUD

https://github.com/grambbledook/indoor-cycling-hud

Tools: C++, Bluetooth Low Energy, QT, sqlite, CMake, vcpkg

Description: An overlay app that aggregates data coming from BLE devices and renders workout

statistics on the heads up display